Finding Aid for the Michael and Susan Kahn Collection of Political Cartoons LSC.2419
UCLA Library Special Collections
Michael and Susan Kahn collection of political cartoons
1690-2022
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kahn, Michael A., 1949-
Kahn, Susan
LSC.2419
43.3 linear feet (20 boxes, 1 map folder)
482 linear feet (482 unprocessed boxes)
The Kahn Collection includes political cartoon art materials created in the United States and internationally covering a variety of subjects offering humorous social commentary and criticism on political topics of the day. The collection totals more than 14,220 items.
Conditions Governing Access
Series 1 and Series 5 are open for research; as the collection is further processed, this finding aid will be updated with changing accessibility conditions. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Portions of collection unprocessed. Material in Series 2-4 and Series 6-9 are unavailable for access. Please see LSC's Access to Unprocessed Collections Policy for more information about levels of discovery and access of special collections materials and registering interest in unprocessed collections.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9997043937106533
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Michael and Susan Kahn, 2023.
Biographical / Historical
Michael Kahn was born in Buffalo, New York on February 4, 1949. He moved to Southern California with Otto, his German immigrant father, and Eleanor, his New York-born mother, in 1951 and attended public schools in Los Angeles. He graduated from James Monroe High School in the San Fernando Valley and attended UCLA from 1966-1970, where he graduated magna cum laude and Phi Beta Kappa and was selected one of twenty honor seniors in a class of several thousand. He subsequently attended Stanford University enrolling simultaneously in the Law School and a PhD political science program. He graduated in 1973 after serving as the book review editor of the Stanford Law Review. He finished the entire PhD program but did not write a thesis and was awarded an MA in Political Science.
In 1973 Mike embarked upon two careers, one as a lawyer and another as a collector of political cartoons. His legal career commenced with a Clerkship with Judge Ben C. Duniway at the Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals in San Francisco and his collecting career commenced with a trove of Puck cartoons purchased at the New Haven Book Barn near Yale. Eventually, Mike would collect tens of thousands of Puck cartoons as he compiled almost a complete run of the magazine which was published from 1877-1918. Mike also co-authored a highly acclaimed book on the history of Puck magazine entitled, What Fools These Mortals Be, the Story of Puck Magazine. Over his fifty-year collecting career Mike exhibited his Puck cartoons numerous times and gave dozens of lectures on the magazine. The highlights of these activities included a memorable program at the New York Historical Society in 2014 introducing the book and a spectacular exhibition of Puck cartoons at the Billy Ireland Museum at the Ohio State University in 2015-2016.
Mike's collecting career took him all over the world as he visited bookstores, museums, antique stores and booksellers' homes to collect books and magazines about or containing political cartoons. Eventually Mike collected cartoons from 59 countries including numerous bound volumes of magazines from the 19th century which were virtually non-existent in the United States. In 2007 Mike displayed the highlights of his collection at the Grolier Club of New York in an exhibition that lasted two months which was accompanied by a catalog containing the best examples of the show. Mike amassed his collection of American cartoons by visiting bookstores and other outlets throughout the United States for over forty years. He also appeared on television shows, panels and programs, radio shows and other media outlets discussing his cartoons. In 2022 his collection was featured in the cover story of Fine Books and Collections magazine. He also sponsored numerous programs which promoted the utilization of political cartoons by secondary and college teachers and professors including the Opper Program at Ohio State University and a lecture series using political cartoons at the University of California, Davis.
In 2005 Mike published the only book ever distributed displaying political cartoons about the Supreme Court and the Constitution entitled May It Amuse the Court. Since then, Mike has delivered dozens of lectures on the subject matter of the book to a wide variety of audiences.
Mike's collecting career overlapped with his legal and political career. He was a trial lawyer and was eventually elected to the California Trial Lawyer Hall of Fame. Mike also served in over a dozen government positions including serving as the head of State agencies under Governors Gray Davis, Arnold Schwarzenegger, and Gavin Newson during California's electricity and wildfire crises. Mike rounded out his activities with service on numerous charitable, civic, and business boards.
In 2022 Mike entered semi-retirement with his wife Susan.
Source: Biography written by donor, Michael Kahn, 2024.
Scope and Contents
The Kahn Collection includes political cartoon art materials created in the United States and internationally covering a variety of subjects offering humorous social commentary and criticism on political topics of the day. The collection totals more than 14,220 items including: approximately 1,047 prints and ephemeral items, 10,778 unbound periodicals, centerspread and single page illustrations, 884 bound periodical volumes, 1,511 books, exhibition catalogs and pamphlets, and 11 record cartons containing research, teaching and subject files. A wide range of different types of works on paper are included in the collection documenting countless subjects and targets of political cartoonists around the world from about 1690 to 2022. Includes original drawings, prints, broadsides, illustrated envelopes, photographs, playing cards, unbound periodicals, bound periodicals, books and pamphlets. Printing methods include engravings, etchings, lithographs, pen and ink, hand coloring, woodblock, presses, and digital printing.
Spanning over three centuries, the Kahn Collection is diverse and international in scope. While many of the subjects are political in nature, there is also a good deal of satirical matter focusing on industry figures, artists, performers, writers, publishers, and others - from well-known celebrity figures to stereotypes of people on all different levels of society. Strengths include: American and British historical political broadsides and prints, newspapers, magazines, bound periodicals and books, pamphlets, and exhibition catalogs; works of Hogarth, Gillray and their contemporaries; portraits and caricatures of Abraham Lincoln and other 19th century American political and industry figures; Thomas Nast published drawings in pamphlets, books, and magazines including Harper's Weekly; and extensive and/or entire runs of some periodicals including Vanity Fair.
The collection includes representation by the cartoonists of at least 59 countries and territories, including: Argentina, Australia, Austria, the Bahamas, Belgium, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Brazil, Burma/Myanmar, Canada, China, Costa Rica, Croatia, Cuba, Czechoslovakia, Denmark, Ecuador, Egypt, Finland, France, German Democratic Republic (East Germany), Germany, Greece, Guatemala, Hungary, India, Iran, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Japan, Mexico, Netherlands/Holland, New Zealand, Nicaragua, Norway, Panama, Peru, Poland, Portugal, Puerto Rico, Romania, Russia/U.S.S.R., Scotland, Serbia, South Africa, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, Tanzania, Turkey, Ukraine, United Kingdom/Great Britain, the United States, Uruguay, Venezuela, Viet Nam and Yugoslavia.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: American Art, Prints, Broadsides and Ephemera, 1798-2020
Series 2: American Unbound Periodicals, 1811-2021
Series 3: American Bound Periodicals, 1842-1968
Series 4: American Books, Exhibition Catalogs and Pamphlets, 1826-2022
Series 5: International Art, Prints, Broadsides and Ephemera, circa 1690-2010
Series 6: International Unbound Periodicals, 1799-2017
Series 7: International Bound Periodicals, 1798-2017
Series 8: International Books, Exhibition Catalogs and Pamphlets, 1715-2022
Series 9: Research, Subject Files and Collection Information, circa 1944-2022
Caricatures and cartoons; Editorial cartoons; Political cartoons; Kahn, Michael A., 1949-; Kahn, Susan
- 1. American Art, Prints, Broadsides and Ephemera, 1798-2020; Series 1; 24.2 linear feet (14 boxes, 1 map folder)
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1 contains approximately 454 original drawings, digital prints, engravings, etchings and ephemeral items. Strengths in print materials depicting American presidential elections of 1828-2020 (with the bulk of items documenting aspects of the elections between 1840 and 1908). Notable items are: the original drawing of Rollin Kirby's Tammany (1928) which received the Pulitzer Prize for its satire on New York's Tammany Hall; several prints each by: Edward Williams Clay, John L. Magee, and David Levine; art, prints, and broadsides in a number of areas in early American history including an engraving by an unknown creator during the Early Republic titled Congressional Pugilists (1798) and several William Charles etchings commentating on the British and the War of 1812 (1812-1815) including: John Bull and His Baltimoreans (1814), Johnny Bull and the Alexandrians (1814), John Bull making a new batch of ships to send to the lakes (circa 1814), and The Hartford Convention (circa 1814); cartoon commentary on the "coffin bills" including James Akins' 1828 lithographic prints The Pedlar and his Pack or the Desperate Effort, an Over Balance; and the rare prints British Warfare in 1812, 1837-38 (1838) and Trouble in the Spartan Ranks (1843). Ephemera group includes some photographic prints and carte-de-visite, postcards, playing cards, illustrated metamorphosis envelopes, illustrated Civil War and World War II envelopes, a musical score and a calendar. Notable items include a clutch of rare illustrated Civil War era envelopes satirizing the capture of Jefferson Davis, carte-de-visite depictions of Davis, and metamorphosis envelopes featuring Martin Van Buren and William Henry Harrison (1840) and A Locofoco Before and After the Late Election: Hurra for Cass! / What! Old Zack Elected! (1848).
  - New York American and Journal - Leander caricatures [postcards], 1906-1907 (Box 132, Folder 10)
    Two postcards feature caricatures of a man or character named "Leander" falling backwards and slipping down steps on a banana peel.
  - Off in a Bunch: The Same Old Races on the Same Old Track, 1908; 1 Print. Adhered to mat board. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Color print depicting a race track showing an animal race on a track with various animals competing. A leader board alongside the track lists names: Bill Taft, Bill Bryan, Gene Chafin, Tommy Hisgen, Tommy Watson, Gene Debs and Preston. These were candidates in the 1908 U.S. presidential election.
  - Bush Cards (Project Pretzel) [playing card set], circa 2002; Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 9)
    Playing card set featuring various political figures from George W. Bush's first presidential term. Features photographs of personalities on cards. www.bushcards.com
  - Bush Cards [first term?] [playing card set], circa 2000; Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 8)
  - Bush Cards: The Second Term [playing card set], 2005; Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 11)
    Playing card set featuring various political figures from George W. Bush's second presidential term. Features photographs of personalities on cards. Only cartoon is on playing card box exterior. Cards are "slanted", not typical playing card shape. www.bushcards.com
  - Bush League Trading Cards [trading card set], circa 1989 (Box 111, Folder 20)
  - California Recall Election Cards [playing card set], circa 2003 (Box 111, Folder 15)
  - California Total Recall [playing card set], circa 2003 (Box 111, Folder 16)
  - Iran-Contra Scandal Trading Cards [trading card set], circa 1987 (Box 111, Folder 19)
  - Iraqi Most Wanted Playing Cards [playing card set], circa 2008 (Box 111, Folder 10)
  - McCain Presidential Playing Cards [playing card set], 2008; Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 12)
    Playing card set featuring various political figures of the McCain presidential run (including media personalities). Features photographs of personalities placed in cartoon backgrounds.
  - Obama Presidential Playing Cards [playing card set], 2008; Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 13)
    Playing card set featuring various political figures of the Obama presidential run (including media personalities). Features photographs of personalities placed in cartoon backgrounds.
  - Obama Presidential Playing Cards: Re-Elect President Obama [playing card set], 2012; Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 14)
    Playing card set featuring various political figures of the Obama administration (including media personalities). Features photographs of personalities placed in cartoon backgrounds.
  - Politicards [playing card set], 1971; Set of playing cards in plastic wrap (no box). (Box 111, Folder 27)
    Playing card set featuring various political figures of the day with a Politicard Scorecard listing which card represents each person.
  - Politicards [playing card set], 1984; Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 1)
  - Politicards 2000 (54 Comic Caricatures) [playing card set], Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 3)
    Playing card set featuring various political figures of the day (including media personalities) with a Politicard Scorecard listing which card represents each person.
  - Politicards 2004 (54 Comic Caricatures) [playing card set], Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 4)
  - Politicards 2008 (54 Comic Caricatures) [playing card set], Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 5)
  - Politicards 2012 (54 cards) [playing card set], Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 6)
  - Politicards 2016 (54 cards) [playing card set], Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 7)
  - Politicards '96 (54 Famous Faces) [playing card set], 1996; Set of playing cards in paper box. (Box 111, Folder 2)
  - President Obama (Inaugural Edition) [trading card set], 2008 (Box 111, Folder 23)
  - Psychedelic Republicans (8 Seriously Groovy Trading Cards) (Series 1, 2, 3) [trading card set], 2003; 3 Trading cards. Set of trading cards in unopened foil wrapper. (Box 111, Folder 24-26)
    Trading cards featuring different designs in each Series 1, 2 and 3. Includes parodies of various political figures associated with the Bush administration including Supreme Court justices.
  - "International Debt Conferences (Listening In)", circa 1945; 1 Print (Box 119, Folder 1)
    Unknown artist for unknown publication at unknown date. Original cartoon drawing, probably pencil and crayon on paper. Depicts a figure who represents "the world" (a well-dressed man in suit, bow tie and top hat with cane, with a globe head and human face) with one hand cupped to his ear near some swinging doors, listening in on conversation. He looks curious and worried. The doors are marked "International Debt Conferences". The drawing is signed "A.V." (sp?) Above the drawing in pencil is written "Listening In". Below the drawing in pencil editorial remarks are noted: 675. 3 cols. P.M. ED. PG. Tues. (possibly indicates this drawing was to be published in a newspaper 3 columns wide in the evening edition on the editorial page on a Tuesday). No text written on verso.
  - Roosevelt: the Peace Victor. The President's Song, 1905; Unbound 3 pages of sheet music with colored cover. (Box 119, Folder 1)
    Sheet music with lyrics regarding the Treaty of Portsmouth that formally ended the Russo-Japanese War (1904-1905). Roosevelt was instrumental in the negotiations and this led to his being awarded the Nobel Peace Prize.
  - Soul Shots: Political Cartoons, 1972; 1 Print. Portfolio folder with individual prints inside. May be missing some prints as not all months in 1969-1972 are represented. (Box 119, Folder 1)
    Includes cartoon reprints by Ollie Harrington published in the Daily World in the German Democratic Republic (East Germany) from 1969-1972.
  - This (1928) Campaign in Cartoons [18 prints in each portfolio], 18 Prints. 2 copies. Prints were contained in acidic envelopes; envelopes have some wear and tear. (Box 119, Folder 2)
    Portfolio envelope with 18 individual prints inside. Published by the New Leader... in the interest of the Socialist Party. "Given at a Socialist meeting!" written in pencil on cover of one envelope.
  - 1991 Bloom County Swimsuit Calendar, 1990; 1 Art calendar. Staple bound wall calendar. (Box 119, Folder 3, Item 5)
  - David Levine 2010 Calendar (The New York Review of Books), 2009; 1 Art calendar. Staple bound wall calendar. (Box 119, Folder 3)
  - David Levine 2012 Calendar: Election Year (The New York Review of Books), 2011; 1 Art calendar (Box 119, Folder 3)
    Includes political caricature cartoons by David Levine of 12 American presidents featured in The New York Review of Books pages over the years, from George Washington to Richard Nixon.
  - Sarah Palin: WTF?! A Parody (The - Did She Really Just Say That? 2011 Calendar), 2010; 1 Art calendar (Box 119, Folder 3)
    Includes political parody in photographs and text. Does not include cartoons.
  - The Twentieth Anniversary Doonesbury 1989-90, 16-Month Wall Calendar, 1 Art calendar. Staple bound wall calendar. (Box 119, Folder 3)
    16 month Doonesbury wall calendar beginning in September 1989 features socially and politically controversial cartoons from Garry Trudeau's career.
  - Congress Drawn... and Quartered! [portfolio with set of 25 autographed drawings], 1985; 25 Prints (Box 119, Folder 4)
    Deluxe edition. Hardbound portfolio with ribbon tie containing paper portfolio with artists' biographies, colophon, unbound title page, list of artists, and signed prints.
  - [Set of 2 illustrated envelopes showing a visibly upset Hitler with the text "Your Axis Partner Gone... Where To now, Schickelgruber?"], 1943-1944 January 2; 2 Envelopes. Illustration is same on both envelopes, but color, date, sender and postmarks are different. (Box 132, Folder 2)
    World War II era illustrated envelopes depicting a visibly upset Hitler with text "Your Axis Partner Gone... Where To now, Schickelgruber?" Each envelope is sent to John C. Felter in Drexel Hill, PA. and sent from Fort Benning, GA. and Scotchtown, Nova Scotia, Canada.
  - [Set of 2 illustrated envelopes showing an American G.I. standing atop Hitler's head as he sleeps with the text "Getting In His Hair"], 1943 July 26-August 12; 2 Envelopes. Illustration is same on both envelopes, but color, date, sender and postmarks are different. (Box 132, Folder 2)
    World War II era illustrated envelopes depicting an American G.I. standing atop Hitler's head (in his dreams?) with text "Getting in his hair." Each envelope is sent to John C. Felter in Drexel Hill, PA. and sent from Louisville, KY.
  - [Set of 3 illustrated envelopes showing an American G.I. kicking a character with the text "Right In Der Fuhrer's Face"], 1943 July11-August 23; 3 Envelopes. Illustration is same on all envelopes, but color, date, sender and postmarks are different. (Box 132, Folder 2)
    World War II era illustrated envelopes depicting an American G.I. kicking a character "Right in der Fuhrer's face." Each envelope is sent to John C. Felter in Drexel Hill, PA. and sent from Louisville, KY. and KellyField, TX.
  - [Set of First Day of Issue "Sunday Funnies" U.S. postage stamps applied to Billy Ireland Cartoon Library & Museum envelope], 2010; 5 postage stamps adhered to envelope. (Box 132, Folder 8)
    Postage stamps feature popular American comic strip characters from: Archie, Garfield, Dennis the Menace, Beetle Bailey and Calvin and Hobbes. Envelope features a return address for the Billy Ireland Cartoon Library & Museum, an ink stamp noting "Sunday Funnies First Day of Issue July 16, 2010 Columbus, OH 43216" and a postmark with same city and date.
  - Baron von Huenefeld, 1928-1936; 1 Print. Pen and ink drawing on paper with editorial marks in pencil. (Box 132, Folder 1)
    Drawing by James House, Jr. dated 1928 depicting Baron von Huenefeld (Ehrenfried Günther Freiherr von Hünefeld). Inscribed to Jean Franchsen (sp?) dated 1936. Includes editorial pencil markup.
  - Caricature of A.T. Stewart [Carte-de-visite], circa 1869 (Box 132, Folder 3)
    Possibly depicts businessman A.T. Turney.
  - Caricature of Dr. Edwin H. Chapin [Carte-de-visite], circa 1867 (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - Caricature of Dr. Henry Whitney Bellows [Carte-de-visite], circa 1865 (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - Caricature of General Mead [Carte-de-visite], circa 1865 (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - Caricature of General Winfield Scott [Carte-de-visite], circa 1860 (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - Caricature of George Bancroft [Carte-de-visite], circa 1870 (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - Caricature of Mayor John T. Hoffman as "Our Mare" [Carte-de-visite], circa 1867 (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - Caricature of Napoleon III with Archduke Maximilian I of Mexico as his puppet [Carte-de-visite], circa 1864 (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - Caricature of unidentified man driving cart pulled by hobby horses [Carte-de-visite], circa 1865 (Box 132, Folder 3)
    Caricature of unidentified man driving cart pulled by hobby horses. The man has a very long, curled mustache and he is holding a whip in one hand and the horse reins in the other hand. His top hat has fallen off behind him and there are bags in his cart, possibly money bags. The man is possibly a banker or railroad baron.
  - Caricature of unidentified man holding binoculars with birds in background [Carte-de-visite], circa 1865 (Box 132, Folder 3)
    Possibly depicts Swiss-born American biologist and geologist Louis Agassiz (1807-1873)
  - Caricature of unidentified man wearing glasses and a three-piece suit with coat tails [Carte-de-visite], circa 1865 (Box 132, Folder 3)
    Caricature of unidentified man wearing glasses and a three-piece suit with coat tails, holding a top hat and staff behind him [Carte-de-visite]
  - Caricature of unidentified Union general [Carte-de-visite], circa 1865 (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - Caricature of Victor Emmanuel II of Italy [Carte-de-visite], circa 1865 (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - Caricature portrait of Mayor Fernando Wood sitting with bat wings and a serpent as the "Angel of Peace" [Carte-de-visite photograph], circa 1860 (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - Cartoon Art Museum Presents: Fundraising Auction of Original Cartoon Art, 1991 July 25; 1 Catalog (Box 132, Folder 11)
    Auction catalog with listings of original cartoon artwork, including Peanuts by Charles Schulz, Dilbert by Scott Adams, Emmy Lou by Marty Links, Wee Pals by Morrie Turner and Doonesbury by Garry Trudeau.
  - Literary Caricatures by David Levine from the New York Review of Books [15 prints with listing page contained in paper presentation folder], 1964; 1 folder containing 15 prints and index page. (Box 132, Folder 6)
    Biographical / Historical
    The New York Review of Books was founded in 1963. David Levine began drawing illustrations for the publication shortly after it was established and drew thousands of caricatures of famous artists, politicians and writers over the course of his career.